# Yuanchun Li

Researcher Systems and Networking Research Area Microsoft Research Asia No. 5 Danling Street, Beijing, China, 100080

Advisors: Chengming Wen

Email: li.yuanchun@foxmail.com Location: Haidian, Beijing, China Website: ylimit.github.io Tel: +86-133-6614-9950

#### **About Me**

I'm a researcher in the Systems and Networking research group at Microsoft Research Asia (MSRA). Before joining MSRA, I obtained Ph.D. and B.S. in Computer Science from Peking University in 2019 and 2014 under the supervision of Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen and Gang Huang. I was also advised by Jason Hong and Yuvraj Agarwal when I was a visiting student in the Human-Computer Interaction Institute at Carnegie Mellon University.

#### **Research Interests**

My research interests lie in the intersection of ubiquitous computing (UbiComp), software engineering (SE), and artificial intelligence (AI), where I've published more than 15 research papers in premier venues such as UbiComp, FSE, and ICSE, including a best paper nomination in UbiComp '2016 and a best paper in IS-EUD '2017. My recent work focuses on the reliablility and privacy issues of AI and AIoT. I enjoy building systems and tools to foster the development of ubiquitously connected world.

| $\mathbf{T}$ | • |   | . •    |  |
|--------------|---|---|--------|--|
| н.           | a | П | cation |  |

| Education  |                   |
|--|-------------------|
| Ph.D., Computer Science, Peking University   | 2014.09 - 2019.06 |
| <ul> <li>Advisors: Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen, Gang Huang</li> </ul>                       |                   |
| Visiting Student, HCII, Carnegie Mellon University                                     | 2016.09 - 2017.09 |
| Advisors: Jason I. Hong, Yuvraj Agarwal  |                   |
| B.S., Computer Science, Peking University  | 2010.09 - 2014.09 |
| Professional Experiences   |                   |
| Researcher, Microsoft Research Asia, Beijing, China                                    | 2019.07 – Now     |
| Systems and Networking Research Area, HEX Group  |                   |
| <ul> <li>Working on reliability and privacy of AI and AIoT</li> </ul>                  |                   |
| Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Redmond, USA                                      | 2018.05 - 2018.08 |
| Advisors: Oriana Riva  |                   |
| <ul> <li>Worked on automatically extracting conversational skills from well</li> </ul> | osites            |
| Software Intern, Xiaomi Monetization Department, Beijing, China                        | 2017.10 - 2018.05 |

Worked on building personal knowledge graphs for privacy-friendly user modeling

# Major Peer-Reviewed Conference and Journal Papers

- 1. **Yuanchun Li**, Jiayi Hua, Haoyu Wang, Chunyang Chen, Yunxin Liu. "DeepBackdoor: Black-box Backdoor Attack on Deep Learning Models through Neural Payload Injection". In Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE/ACM 39th International Conference on Software Engineering. (ICSE 2021).
- 2. Bingyan Liu(intern), **Yuanchun Li\***, Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen, Yunxin Liu. "PMC: A Privacy-preserving Deep Learning Model Customization Framework for Edge Computing". Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol. 4, 4, Article 139 (December 2020), 25 pages. (UbiComp 2021).
- 3. Ziqi Zhang(intern), **Yuanchun Li\***, Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen, Yunxin Liu. "Dynamic Slicing for Deep Neural Networks." In Proceedings of the 28th ACM Joint Meeting on European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering. Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 838–850. (ESEC/FSE 2020)
- 4. **Yuanchun Li**, Ziyue Yang\*, Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen. "Humanoid: a deep learning-based approach to automated black-box Android app testing." In Proceedings of the 34th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering. IEEE Press, 1070–1073. (ASE 2019 Tool).
- 5. **Yuanchun Li**, Ziyue Yang, Yao Guo, Xiangqun Chen, Yuvraj Agarwal, and Jason Hong. "Automated Extraction of Personal Knowledge from Smartphone Push Notifications." The IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 733-742. (BigData 2018)
- 6. Yao Guo, **Yuanchun Li**, Ziyue Yang, and Xiangqun Chen. "What's inside your app?: Understanding Feature Redundancy in Mobile Apps." In Proceedings of the IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension, 266-276. (ICPC 2018)
- 7. Haojian Jin, Minyi Liu, Kevan Dodhia, **Yuanchun Li**, Gaurav Srivastava, Matthew Fredrikson, Yuvraj Agarwal, and Jason I. Hong. 2018. Why Are They Collecting My Data? Inferring the Purposes of Network Traffic in Mobile Apps. Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol. 2, 4, Article 173 (December 2018), 27 pages. (UbiComp 2020)
- 8. **Yuanchun Li**, Fanglin Chen, Toby Jia-Jun Li, Yao Guo, Gang Huang, Matthew Fredrikson, Yuvraj Agarwal, and Jason I. Hong. "PrivacyStreams: Enabling Transparency in Personal Data Processing for Mobile Apps." Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol. 1, 3, Article 76 (September 2017), 26 pages. (UbiComp 2017)
- 9. **Yuanchun Li**, Baoxiong Jia, Yao Guo, and Xiangqun Chen. "Mining User Reviews for Mobile App Comparisons." Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol. 1, 3, Article 75 (September 2017), 15 pages. (UbiComp 2017)
- 10. Haoyu Wang, **Yuanchun Li**, Yao Guo, Yuvraj Agarwal, and Jason I. Hong. "Understanding the Purpose of Permission Use in Mobile Apps." ACM Trans. Inf. Syst. 35, 4, Article 43 (July 2017), 40 pages. (TOIS 2017)
- 11. **Yuanchun Li**, Ziyue Yang, Yao Guo and Xiangqun Chen. "DroidBot: A Lightweight UI-Guided Test Input Generator For Android." In Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE/ACM 39th International Conference on Software Engineering Companion, 321-326. (ICSE 2017 Tool)
- 12. Toby Jia-Jun Li, **Yuanchun Li**, Fanglin Chen and Brad A. Myers. "Programming IoT Devices by Demonstration Using Mobile Apps." End-User Development. International Symposium on End User Development, 3-17. (IS-EUD 2017, **Best Paper Award**)
- 13. **Yuanchun Li**, Yao Guo, and Xiangqun Chen. "PERUIM: Understanding Mobile Application Privacy with Permission-UI Mapping." In Proceedings of the 2016 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing, 682-693. (UbiComp 2016, **Best Paper Honorable Mention Award**)

14. **Yuanchun Li**, Yao Guo, Junjun Kong and Xiangqun Chen. "Fixing Sensor-Related Energy Bugs Through Automated Sensing Policy Instrumentation." IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Low Power Electronics and Design, 321-326. (ISLPED 2015)

# **Open-Source Software**

I authored several open-source tools that are popular in my research area.

- DroidBot A Lightweight UI-Guided Test Input Generator (500+ stars)
  - o https://github.com/honeynet/droidbot
- PrivacyStreams A Library for Easy and Secure Personal Data Processing (200+ stars)
  - o https://github.com/PrivacyStreams/PrivacyStreams

# Selected Honors, Grants and Awards

| • | National Scholarship   | 2017 |
|---|--|------|
| • | IS-EUD Best Paper Award  | 2017 |
| • | Bosch/Bezirk Internet of Things Hackathon - 1st place (\$1000) | 2016 |
| • | UbiComp Best Paper Honorable Mention Award                     | 2016 |
| • | Google Summer of Code (\$5500)                                 | 2016 |
| • | Merit Student at Peking University                             | 2016 |
| • | Google Summer of Code (\$5500)                                 | 2015 |

# **Teaching Experience**

| • | Instructor, AI Systems Course                           | Online course            |
|---|---|--------------------------|
|   | o https://github.com/microsoft/AI-System                |                          |
| • | Teaching Assistant, Operating System Labs (honor track) | Fall 2014, Spring 2015   |
|   |   | Fall 2015, Spring 2016   |
| • | Teaching Assistant, Compiler Techniques                 | Spring 2015, Spring 2016 |
| • | Teaching Assistant, Introduction to Computer Systems    | Fall 2013, Fall 2014     |
| • | Mentor, Google Summer of Code                           | Summer 2015, Summer 2016 |

### Languages and Skills

- Language Chinese (Mandarin) Native
- Language English Professional working proficiency
- Programming Languages Python, Java, C++, JavaScript, Scala, SQL, Lisp
- Techniques Program analysis, reinforcement learning, applied machine learning